INSTRUCTOR: Hello, my name is Uma.
I'm a PhD candidate here at MIT, and I'll
be guiding you through this lecture
on multimodal, multitask machine learning in health care.
In this lecture, we'll explore how
combining different types of medical data, as you have seen
in previous lectures, such as images
and clinical notes, along with a new concept,
multitask learning, which makes multiple clinical predictions
simultaneously, can be integrated
to make better predictions.
To understand why multimodal, multitask
machine learning matters today, it's
useful to take a step back and look
at where we are with existing clinical support tools.
This chart that you see here lays out
several very well-known clinical models in terms of their two
key axes.
On the y-axis, we consider how general the data sources
are, from very simple demographic features
to rich high-dimensional modalities,
like images, language, and multisource data.
On the x-axis, we measure how general
the tasks are from a single clinical prediction
in a specific setting, to more ambitious models that
aim to make many predictions across multiple clinical
domains.
Every single reference here corresponds
to a landmark paper or system, and you'll
notice that most existing tools actually
cluster around the bottom left, which kind of correspond
to the single-task models that rely on very limited data types.
And even some of the more advanced models,
like those using general EHR data, image data, language data,
still actually operate within one clinical setting
or a problem class.
But more recent works, marked here in blue,
aims to actually push that boundary a little bit more,
which implies can we possibly learn across multiple data
sources and across multiple clinical tasks
at once and simultaneously.
In this module, we'll talk about how this paradigm shift, which
tours multimodal multitask machine learning,
can really help us build smarter models for healthcare decision
support.
To begin, let's take a look at how model selection is actually
traditionally done in health care machine learning.
Suppose we're trying to solve one clinical problem.
We would typically split the data set into training
and testing sets, run cross-validation
over several model types, and then select the model
with the best average performance
on that particular task.
And after verifying it performs well on a test set,
we'll deploy it in practice.
So this is a very solid and very widely adopted
approach, both in academia as well as in industry.
But here's a small catch.
It only treats each clinical task in isolation.
For instance, we might separately build models
for deterioration prediction, procedure scheduling,
surgical planning, or even domestic violence prevention.
And each of them gets its own model
being trained completely independently,
optimized independently, and being deployed independently.
But what are we really leaving on the table
with this in-silo approach?
In many cases, these tasks are not really truly independent,
but rather patterns that help predict
deterioration could potentially signal a longer length of stay.
So think about this patient's condition simply
not being very healthy and they deteriorated,
which will prolong the entire stay of their hospital
admission.
Information being very useful for procedure scheduling
might also overlap with insights from surgical planning.
So the question becomes, if I stick with the classical model
selection, one task, one model at a time,
what are some of the shared signals that we are discarding?
Can we potentially do better by learning across these tasks
jointly?
So let's try to dive into one very concrete example,
cardiology.
Traditionally, as we have said, AI models
are very much built to predict a single cardiac condition.
For instance, we might train a model
to predict ejection fraction based
on some EKG data or a separate model
to predict sudden cardiac death.
So these are very powerful tools in isolation.
And as we see in literature, as well as in practice,
a lot of their performances are very, very strong.
But they are missing something critical,
which are these clinical context doesn't always happen in silo.
They think about in terms of the patient
and how these risks actually interact with each other.
So instead of building a single model per outcome,
we actually aim to build models that can simultaneously
predict multiple cardiac endpoints
and in this case, a single model that jointly predicts ejection
fraction and sudden cardiac death
from the same time series and EKG data.
So why does this matter?
Because shared physiological signals,
like irregular rhythms, waveform patterns, or vital sign shift,
may be relevant across multiple conditions.
And by training on these tasks together,
the model can learn shared representations
and become more clinically insightful.
We also see a very similar opportunity in oncology,
where most existing AI models in cancer care
are really designed to predict a single endpoint.
For example, one model might classify
whether a tumor is malignant or benign,
while the other model estimates the stage of cancer
once it's been diagnosed.
And these models tend to work completely independently,
even though both predictions rely on overlapping patient
data, like genetics, pathology reports, or EHR information.
But again, from a clinical perspective,
these outcomes are very much deeply connected to each other.
You don't just want to know if someone has cancer.
You also want to know how far it has already progressed
and how aggressively it should be treated.
And that's why our goal is to move towards models that, again,
jointly predict multiple oncology
endpoints, like classification and staging,
at the exact same time.
And in this particular case, we'll
be using genetics and structure EHR data
to drive these predictions.
And the hope is that, again, some
shared biological signals, either genetic mutations,
biomarkers, treatment response patterns,
can potentially enrich both tasks
while being learned together.
And this type of multitask setup really
allows us to make diagnostic tools that
feel closer to how oncologists actually think.
So in both cardiology and oncology,
we saw that clinical tasks don't happen in isolation.
Conditions co-occur.
Diagnostics are interconnected.
And treatment decisions often depend
on multiple, simultaneous diagnostic predictions.
So a natural question becomes, how
can we potentially design models that actually learn
all of these outcomes together?
And instead of treating each one on its own problem,
the core idea is this, rather than
training a single model per outcome,
let's train a single model that can learn multiple clinically
relevant tasks at once.
And mathematically speaking, we are given an input x.
This is precisely the exact same as a single task problem
that we have seen up until this point.
But instead of building m--
think about this as m different types of endpoints, conditions
that we're considering.
Instead of building m separate models
to predict different types of outcome,
y1, y2 all the way to ym, let's try to learn a joint function
f that outputs all of them simultaneously.
The way which we can accomplish this
is through multitask learning, which
is a branch of technique from the computer science community,
recently explored across a lot of different areas.
And the core idea is the availability
of a shared learning component.
But what exactly is the intuition of this setup?
And why would it actually improve performance?
This particular slide that you see next
illustrates precisely the core intuition.
On the left, we have a standard approach
to separate models trained independently
to predict two outcomes A and B. Every single model you see
receives the same input embedding, which
is a fixed-length, numerical representation of the data,
in this case a patient.
But because there are no shared learning,
the two tasks cannot benefit from each other.
Maybe model A learns something useful about comorbidities
or lab values that could have helped model B,
but that information never gets transferred.
On the right, however, we have a shared learning network
for multitask learning.
And remember, this really is the key for multitask learning.
Now, the same input goes through this shared layers,
whose parameters are being jointly optimized and jointly
learned from both tasks.
And what happens here is very important.
The model begins to learn more generalizable patterns that are
useful across both outcomes.
And it can focus on commonalities, for example,
elevated inflammation or shared risk markers,
and refine them jointly together,
which is precisely what leads to these more accurate and stable
predictions.
And let's try and go one layer slightly deeper
into the training, as well as inference process.
In multitask learning, we're not just
sharing these model parameters.
We're actually augmenting the data implicitly
by exposing every single task to information from others.
During training, when we are computing the loss for task A,
that loss back propagates through the shared network,
updating the parameters.
But later, when we're trying to train task B,
it benefits from that trained, updated shared network,
meaning that task A's signal has now indirectly helped
with task B's learning.
So even though we don't directly feed task A's outcome
into task B's input, it is as if task B
has access to the hidden representation of information
regarding task A's outcome.
And you can think about this as a very subtle form
or implicit form of data augmentation,
where we are enriching every training
example by letting related outcomes inform one another.
And during inference, we don't need
both labels or both outcomes, really just the input.
But the model already carries these shared representation
during training, which can then lead to stronger generalization.
So when the tasks are related, multitask learning
creates a kind of implicit collaboration,
where each task becomes a teacher for the others.
And this is exactly what we mean when
we say multitask models are more than the sum of their parts.
Before we move on, let's clarify how multitask learning differs
from another very common strategy, transfer learning.
On the left, we see transfer learning in action.
And this is a sequential approach,
where first a model is trained on task A, typically
a large or general purpose task.
Then that trained model, or some part of it, is transferred
and fine tuned on task B. This works
very well when you don't have much data for the second task,
and the first task is similar enough
to provide a meaningful head start.
But notice that learning is one directional,
where task A informs task B, but not the other way around.
Now contrast with multitask learning, shown on the right.
Here you see multiple tasks, say tasks A, B, and C,
are being trained together simultaneously through a shared
learning representation.
And every single task both teaches as well as
learns from the others.
And these shared layers are being updated jointly
so that every gradient step is informed by multiple objectives.
And this two-way communication is what gives multitask learning
its power where especially in domains
like health, where outcomes are naturally interrelated.
So while both methods aim to reuse knowledge,
multitask learning is a more collaborative process, not just
a handoff from one task to another.
And that collaboration often leads to better generalization,
faster learning, and also deeper representation
of the original information.
So far, we've talked about why multitask learning is
powerful on its own, but in health care,
we often have another challenge, but also
from another angle, opportunity, which
is the presence of multiple data modalities.
So think about a typical hospital setting.
You have images like X-ray MRIs, tabular data, like demographics
and lab values, time series, like vitals,
as well as monitoring of your heart rate,
language data from clinical notes and EKG reports.
Each of these data types really carries
complementary information about the patient,
but integrating them into a single model is nontrivial.
And this brings us to the key idea of our framework.
So first we'll extract features from each modality using
finetuned models, like a CNN from images or transformers
for clinical notes.
Then we align these features into a shared-learning embedding
space, using contrastive learning,
to make sure that the representations
from different modalities are compatible.
Once we have that unified representation,
we pass it into a shared learning network,
often with task-specific branches
and shared attention blocks to really support
multitask prediction.
And finally, we produce a task-specific output,
like prediction of heart failure, which
is a binary classification problem;
chest pathology identification, a multiclass classification
problem; length of stay, a regression problem;
or patient subgroupings, an unsupervised cluster.
And a nice property of this framework
is that it's very modular, where if you
have a new modality of data or a new task
that you're interested in learning more about,
you can add them without redesigning the entire pipeline.
It is also scalable because everything
is trained end to end.
This is what makes it truly multimodal and multitask,
a single model that pulls insights
from a diverse clinical data modalities to try
and power through a wide range of medical predictions.